前面两节中，我们讨论了CBC-MAC和NMAC
In the last two segments we talked about
the CBC-MAC and NMAC to convert a PRF for
将一个处理短信息的PRF转换成一个处理长信息的PRF
small messages into a PRF for much larger
messages. Those two constructions were
这两个MAC机制是串行的，意思是即使你有多个处理器
sequential, in the sense that if you had
multiple processors you couldn't make the
你也不能让它们工作的更快。本节我们看一种并行MAC
construction work any faster. In this
segment we're gonna look at a parallel MAC
也是把一个小PRF转成了大PRF
that also converts a small PRF into a
large PRF, but does it in a very
不过是可并行的。特别地，我们将看到一种并行的MAC机制
parallelizable fashion. In particular we're
gonna look at a parallel MAC construction
叫做PMAC，它使用了一个底层PRF，来构建一个PRF
called PMAC, that uses an underlying PRF
to construct a PRF for much larger
去处理长得多的信息。特别地，这个PRF可以处理长得多
messages. In particular, the PRF can
process much longer messages that can have
具有可变长度、最多L个分组的信息
variable length and have as many as L
blocks in them. Now the construction works
这个机制如下工作。我们取信息，把它分成若干分组
as follows. We take our message and we
break it into blocks. And then we process
然后我们独立地处理各个分组。首先，我们计算
each block independently of the other. So,
the first thing we do, is we evaluate some
某个函数P并将结果与第一个分组异或
function P and we XOR the result
into the first message block, and then we
然后我们运用函数F，使用密钥k1。
我们对每个分组都做同样的事情
apply our function F using a key k1.
We do the same for each one of the
大家注意，我们可以并行地处理
message blocks and you notice that we can
do it all parallel, all message blocks are
所有分组被独立地处理。我们收集来所有的结果
processed independently of one another.
And we collect all these results into some
然后异或起来，然后再加密一次，就得到了最后的标签
final XOR and then we encrypt one more time
to get the final tag value. Now for a
由于技术原因，在最后一个分组上，我们不需要
technical reason, actually on the very
last one. We actually don't need to apply
使用PRF F了。如我所说，这是由于技术原因
the PRF F, but as I said, this is just
for technical reason, and I'm going to
我这里先不讲。现在我想解释一下这个函数P是干什么的
ignore that for now. Now, I want to
explain what the function P is for and
设想一下，如果函数P不在这
what it does. So imagine, just for a
second, that the function P isn't actually
我们想像一下，直接把每条信息输入PRF
there. That is, imagine we actually,
directly feed each message block into the
不进行任何处理。那么我说
PRF without applying any other
processing to it. Then I claim that the
得到的MAC是完全不安全的，原因是
resulting MAC is completely insecure and
the reason is essentially no order is
各个分组之间没有加入先后顺序。
特别地，如果我交换两个分组
enforced between the message blocks. In
particular, if I swap two message blocks,
将不会改变最后标签的值。因为异或是可交换的
that doesn't change the value of the final
tag. Because the XOR is commutative, the
无论我们是否交换分组，标签值都是一样的
tag will be the same whether we swap the
blocks or not. As a result, an attacker
因此攻击者可以请求一个特定信息的标签
can request the tag for a particular
message, and then he obtains the tag for a
然后他获得了将其中两分组交换后的信息的标签
message where two of the blocks are
swapped and that counts as an existential
这也算存在性伪造。这个函数P试图为这些分组加入顺序
forgery. So what this function P tries to
do is essentially enforce order on these
首先大家注意到，这个函数P是个带密钥的函数
blocks. And you notice that the function
takes, first of all, it's a keyed function,
他取密钥为输入。其次，更为重要的
so it takes a key as input. And second of
all, more importantly, it takes the block
它取分组序数为输入。换句话说，函数的这个输入
number as input. In other words, the
value of the function is different for
每个分组都不相同。这就是用来阻止
each one of the blocks. And that's
actually exactly what's preventing this,
分组交换攻击的。函数P其实是一个非常容易计算的函数
blocks swapping attack. So the function P
actually, is a very easy to compute
给了密钥和分组序号
function. Essentially given the key and
the message block, all it is, is just a
P只是进行了某个有限域上的乘法。所以
这是个非常容易计算的函数
multiplication in some finite fields. So
it's a very, very simple function to
对于PMAC的运行时间开销很小
compute. It adds very little to the
running time of PMAC. And yet, it's
这也足以保证PMAC的安全性。我们说过
enough in ensure that the PMAC is
actually secure. As we've said, the key
PMAC的密钥是一对密钥，一个密钥是给PRF的
另一个密钥是给这个掩码函数P的
for PMAC is this pair of keys. One key for
the PRF, and one key for this masking
最后我会告诉大家，如果信息长度不是
function P. And finally, I'll tell you
that if the message length is not a
分组长度的倍数，也就是最后一个分组
multiple of the block length. That is,
imagine the last block is shorter than
比满分组长度短，那么PMAC实际上使用了一个
与CMAC类似的补齐方法
full block length, then PMAC actually uses
a padding that's similar to CMAC, so that
这样是不需要加假的分组的
there is no need for an additional dummy
block, ever. So that's the PMAC
这时PMAC的构建，与往常一样，我们看它的安全性定理
construction and as usual, we can state
its security theorem. So the security
大家应该习惯这种安全性定理了。
这个定理说，如果给我
theorem, by now, you should be used to it.
Essentially, it says that if you give me
一个攻击PMAC的攻击者，我可以构建另一个
an adversary attacking PMAC, I can
construct an adversary attacking the
攻击底层PRF的攻击者，加上另一个误差项
underlying PRF. Plus an additional error
term. And so, since again, the PRF is
由于这个PRF是安全的，我们知道这一项是可忽略的
如果我们希望这一项是可忽略的
secure, we know that this term is
negligible. And so if we want this term to
我们需要这一误差项也是可忽略的
be negligible, we know that, we need this
error term to also be negligible. Here, as
与往常一样，q是使用一个密钥计算MAC的信息数
usual, q is the number of messages that
are MAC-ed using a particular key. And L
L是所有这些信息的最大长度。PMAC是安全的
is the maximum length of all those
messages. And PMAC is secure, as long as
只要它的乘积小于分组大小的平方根。对于AES
its product is less than the square root
of the block size. So for AES, this would be
分组大小是2的128次方，其平方根是2的64次方
two to the 128, and the square root,
therefore, would be two to the 64th. So the
这个MAC将是安全的，只要q乘以L小于2的64次方
MAC would be secure, as long as Q times L
is less than two to the 64th. And every time,
每次当它接近这个值时，你当然必须更换密钥
as it gets closer to that value, of
course, you would have to change the key
为了计算更多信息的MAC。这里主要记住一点
in order to continue MAC-ing more
messages. So the main thing to remember is
PMAC也给了我们一个PRF，当它独立地处理这些信息分组时
that PMAC also gives us a PRF, and when it
processes the message blocks independently
PMAC也有个非常有趣的性质
of one another. Turns out that PMAC also
has a very interesting property. Namely,
PMAC的数学是增长的。我来为大家解释一下什么意思
that PMAC math is incremental. So let me
explain to you what that means. So suppose
假设用来构建PMAC的函数F不仅是PRF
the function F that's used to construct PMAC
is not just a PRF, but, in fact, a
而且而是PRP，那么我们能在需要时求F的逆
permutation, PRP. So we can actually
invert it when we need to. Now suppose
现在假设我们已计算长信息m的MAC
we've already computed the MAC for a
particularly long message m. And now,
假设这个长信息的一个分组发生了变化
suppose just one message block of this
long message changes. So here, m[1] has
这里m[i]变成了m'[1]，但其他分组不变
changed into m'[1]. But the
remaining message blocks all remain the
对于其他MAC机制，比如CBC-MAC，即使只有一个分组变化了
same. For other MAC-s, like CBC-MAC, even
though only one message block changed, you
你还是需要重新计算整个信息的标签
would have to recompute the tag on the
entire message. Recomputing the tag
重新计算标签需要的时间与信息长度成正比
basically will take time that's
proportional to the length of the message.
实际上用PMAC，如果我们只变化一个分组
It turns out, with PMAC, if we only
change one block, or a small number of
或是很少的分组，我们可以很快就完成标签的重新计算
blocks, actually, we can recompute the
value of the tag for the new message very,
让我考一考大家，看看你能不能想到办法
very quickly. And let me ask you a puzzle
to see if you can figure out how to do
记住函数F是PRP，所以是可逆的
that yourself. And remember, the function
F is a PRP, and therefore is invertible.
我们看，你能否自己想出如何计算新信息的MAC
So let's see if you can figure out how to
compute the MAC in the new message by
这是可以的。你可以很快重新计算
yourself. So it turns out this can be
done. And you can quickly recompute the
新信息的标签，通过使用这里的第三行。
为确保我们都能理解这个答案
tag on the new message using this third
line here. Just to make sure we all see
我们简单回顾一下PMAC的最初图表
the solution, let's quickly go back to the
original diagram for PMAC and I can show
我能展示我的意思。那么想象这个信息分组
you what I mean. So imagine this one
message block changed into some other
变成了某个其他分组，即M'[1]。然后我们就可以
block, say, it changed into M'[1]. Then
what we could do is we can take the tag on
取改变前原信息的标签，我们可以求函数F的逆
the original message before the change was
made. So we can invert the function F, and
确定应用函数F之前的值。现在由于我们有了
determine the value before the function F
was applied. Now, well, since we now have
这些分组的异或值，我们可以抵消掉
an XOR of a bunch of blocks, what
we can do is we can cancel out the XOR
来自原分组的异或部分，通过将这个值
that came from the original message block,
basically by XOR-ing this value that came
与原信息分组传到这个异或加法器的值进行异或
from the original message block into this
XOR-ed accumulator. And then XOR-ing again
再异或来自新分组传到这个异或加法器的值
the value that would come from the new
message block back into the XOR
然后再应用函数F，就得到新信息的标签
accumulator. And then apply the function F
again. And that will give us the tag for
只改变了一个分组。用符号的话
the new message, where just one block was
changed. So in symbols, basically, I wrote
我把公式写在这了。大家可以看到，我们对标签进行解密
the formula over here. You can see,
basically, we decrypt the tag, and then we
然后我们把结果与这个来自原分组的值进行异或
XOR with the block that comes from the
original message block. We XOR again with
(这里第一个block并非分组)
再把结果与来自新分组的值进行异或
the block that comes from the new message
block. And then we re-encrypt the final
然后我们重新加密最后这个异或加法器的输出
以获得新信息的标签，只改变一个分组
XOR accumulator to get the new tag for the
message with a one block changed. So
这是个美观的性质。这证明了如果你有很长的信息
that's kind of a neat property. It kind of
shows that if you have very large
你可以很快地更新标签。当然你需要密钥
messages, you can very quickly update the
tag. Of course you would need the secret
来完成更新，但你可以快速更新标签，
如果仅有少量分组被改变了
key to do the update, but you can quickly
update the tag if just a small number of
好的，我们的PMAC讨论到此为止
message blocks changed. Okay, so that
concludes our discussion of PMAC. And now
现在我想换一点话题，讨论一次性MAC的概念
I wanna switch topics a little bit, and
talk about the concept of a one time MAC,
这与一次性密码本类似，但是是关于完整性的
which is basically the analog of the one
time pad, but in the world of integrity.
那么我解释一下我的意思。想像一下，我们构建了一个MAC
So let me explain what I mean by that. So
imagine we wanna build a MAC that is only
它只用于单个信息的完整性。换句话说，每次计算
used for integrity of a single message. In
other words, every time we compute the
特定信息的完整性，我们也要改变密钥
integrity of a particular message, we also
change the key. So that any particular key
任何密钥只能用于一条信息的完整性。然后
我们可以定义安全性游戏
is used only for integrity of one message.
Then we can define the security game as
就是说攻击者看一条信息。所以
basically saying, the attacker's gonna see
one message. Therefore, we only allow him
我们只允许他做一次选择信息攻击。那么
他提交一个信息的询问
to do one chosen message attack. So he
gets to submit one message query, and he
他得到了这个询问信息对应的标签。现在
is given the tag corresponding to that one
message query. And now his goal is to
攻击者的目标是伪造一对信息-标签。好
大家可以看到它的目标是产生
forge a message tag pair. Okay, so you
can see his goal was to produce one
一个信息-标签对，可以正确验证的，并且与
攻击者得到的信息-标签对不一样的
message tag pair that verifies correctly and
is different from the pair that he was
我们会看到，就像一次性密码本和流密码那样非常有用
actually given. As we'll see, just like
the one time pad and stream ciphers were
一次性MAC对同样的应用也是很有用的
quite useful, it turns out one time MAC-s
are also quite useful for the same
当我们只想使用一个密钥，为单条信息
提供加密或完整性
applications when we only wanna use a key
to encrypt or to provide integrity for
通常，我们说一次性MAC是安全的
just a single message. So as usual we
would say that a one time MAC is secure,
因为没有攻击者可以赢得这场游戏。现在有趣的是
because basically no adversary can win
this game. Now the interesting thing is
一次性MAC就像一次性密码本一样，
对无限强力的攻击者都是安全的
that one time MAC-s, just like the one time
pad can be secure against infinitely
不仅如此，因为它们是只为一次性使用设计的
powerful adversaries. And not only that,
because they're only designed to be secure
它们可以比基于PRF的MAC更快
for one time use, they can actually be
faster than MAC-s that are based on PRFs.
我只想给大家一个一次性MAC的简单例子
And so I just wanted to give you a quick
example of one one time MAC, this is a
这是一个一次性MAC的经典机制，我来展示它的工作过程
classic construction for a one time MAC,
let me show you how it works. The first
首先，选取一个比分组大小略大的质数
step is to pick a prime that's slightly
larger than our block size. In this case
当我们使用128位分组时，我们选的第一个质数
we're going to use 128-bit blocks, so
let's pick the first prime that's bigger
大于2的128次方。质数选为2的128次方加51
than two to the 128th. This happens to be
two to the 128th plus 51. And now the key
现在这个密钥是一对随机数，它们的取值范围
从1到我们选的质数，从1到q
is going to be a pair of random numbers in
the range 1 to our prime, so 1 to q. So we
我们选了两个随机数，范围从1到q。现在我们有了一个信息
choose two random integers in the range 1
to q. Now we're given a message so we're
我们取信息，把它分成若干分组，每个分组128位
going to take our message and break it
into blocks where each block is 128 bits,
我们把每个分组里的数视为整数，范围从0
and we're going to regard each number as
an integer in the range 0 to 2 to the
到2的128次方减一。现在MAC如下定义。首先
128th minus 1. Now the MAC is defined as
follows. The first thing we do is we take
我们去我们的信息分组，构建它们的多项式
our message blocks and we kind of
construct the polynomial out of them. So
如果信息中有L个分组，我们构建一个
if there are L blocks in our message,
we're going to construct the polynomial of
L次多项式，大家注意多项式的常数项设为0
degree L and you notice that the constant
term of the polynomial is set to zero. And
然后我们非常简单地定义MAC
then we define the MAC very simply.
Basically what we do is we take the
我们去信息对应的多项式，计算它在点K的值
polynomial that corresponds to the
message, we evaluate it at the point K
K是我们密钥的一半，然后我们加上A
that's one half of our secret key, and
then we add the value A which is the
A是我们密钥的另一半。完事了，这就是整个MAC
second half of our secret key. And that's
it. That's the whole MAC. So just
构建我们信息对应的多项式
basically construct the polynomial that
corresponds to our message, evaluate that
计算多项式在我们密钥的一半的值，然后再加上另一半密钥
polynomial at half of the secret key, and
add the other half of the secret key to
当然最后结果取模q。好，整个MAC就是这些
the result, and of course reduce final
result modulo q. Okay so that's it, so
这是一次性安全MAC，我们会证明这个MAC
the whole MAC, it's a one time secure MAC
and we will argue that this MAC is one
是一次性安全的，通过证明
如果我告诉你一个特定信息的MAC值
time secure, essentially by arguing that
if I tell you the value of MAC for one
并不会告诉你任何关于另一信息的MAC的任何信息
particular message, that tells you nothing
at all about the value of the MAC at
因此，即使你已经看过一条信息的MAC
another message. And as a result, even
though you've seen the value of the MAC on
你也无法伪造其他信息的MAC
a particular message, you have no way of
forging this MAC on some other message.
现在我强调，这是一次性MAC，但不是二次安全的
Now I should emphasize that this is a one
time MAC, but it's not two time secure. In
换句话说，如果你看到了两条不同信息的MAC
other words, if you get to see the value
of the MAC on two different messages, that
那将完全暴露了密钥，你就可以预测
actually completely compromises the
secret key. And you can actually predict a MAC
你选的第3、第4条信息的MAC了。这样MAC就是可伪造的了
for a third or fourth message of your
choice. So then the MAC becomes forgeable.
但是对于一次性使用，它是完美安全的MAC
But for one time use, it is a perfectly
secure MAC, and I'll tell you that in fact
我告诉大家事实上，它是一个算起来非常快的MAC。
我们已经构建了一次性MAC
it's a very fast MAC to evaluate. So now
that we've constructed one time MAC-s,
实际上有一个通用方法，可以把一次性MAC
turns out there's actually a general
technique that will convert one time MAC-s
转变成多次MAC。我只想简单展示一下如何工作
into many time MAC-s. And I just wanted to
briefly show you how that works. So
假设我们有一次性MAC，签名和验证算法分别记为S和V
suppose we have our one time MAC, let's
call it S and V for signing and
我们假设签名本身是n位字符串
verification algorithms, and let's just
assume that the tags themselves are n bit
另外，我们看一个安全的PRF
strings. In addition, let's also look at a
PRF, a secure PRF, that also happens to
它也正好输出n位字符串，但也取n位字符串
output n bit strings but also takes as
inputs n bit strings. So let's now define
我们现在定义一个通用的MAC构建。
这些MAC叫做Carter-Wegman MAC
a general construction for a MAC. These
MAC-s are called Carter-Wegman MAC-s that
它们如下工作。我们对信息M应用一次性MAC
works as follows. Basically what we would
do is we would apply the one time MAC to
然后我们用PRF加密结果
the message M and then we're going to
encrypt the results using the PRF. So how do
如何加密结果呢？我们选择一个随机数r
we encrypt the result? Well, we choose a
random r and then we compute kind of a
根据r计算一个一次性密码本，通过对r应用PRF
one time pad from this r by applying the
PRF to it. And then we XOR the result
然后我们把结果与一次性MAC异或。这个机制漂亮的一点是
with the actual one time MAC. So the neat
thing about this construction is that the
快速的一次性MAC被用到了可能有几个G的长信息上
fast one time MAC is applied to the long
message, which could be gigabytes long.
而费时的PRF只被应用在新鲜值r上
And the slower PRF is only applied to this
nonce r, which is then used to
r接着被用来加密MAC的最后结果。
大家可以证明如果我们的MAC
encrypt the final results of the MAC. And
you can argue that if the MAC that was
作为构建分组，是个安全的MAC，而PRF也是安全的
given to us as a building block is a one
time secure MAC, and the PRF is secure,
那么事实上，我们可以获得一个多次的安全MAC
其输出2n位标签
then, in fact, we get a many time secure
MAC that happens to output 2n bit tags.
我们待会看Carter-Wegman MAC，当我们讨论
So we're gonna see Carter-Wegman MAC-s later
on when we talk about authenticated
认证加密时。事实上，NIST的一个标准的完整性加密方法
encryption. And, in fact, one of the NIST standard
methods for doing encryption with
使用了Carter-Wegman MAC来提供完整性
integrity, uses a Carter-Wegman MAC for
providing integrity. I want to mention
妄想税这个Carter-Wegman MAC是个随机MAC的好例子
that this Carter-Wegman MAC is a good
example of a randomized MAC where this nonce
这个新鲜值r每次重新计算标签时，都被重新选取
r is chosen afresh every time the tag is
computed. And so for example if you try to
如果你试图两次计算同一信息的标签，
你会选择一个不同的r
compute a tag for the same message twice
each time you'll choose a different r and
因此两次你会得到不同的标签。这是MAC的一个好例子
as a result you'll get different tags both
times. And so this is a nice example of a
这个MAC不是基于PRF的
MAC that's actually not a pseudo random
function, not a PRF, because a single
因为单个信息可以被映射到许多不同的标签
message could actually be mapped to many
different tags all of which are valid for
所有的标签对这个信息都是有效的。
总结一下Carter-Wegman MAC
that one message. To conclude our
discussion on the Carter-Wegman MAC, let me
我问大家下面这个问题。这里我们有
Carter-Wegman MAC的方程
ask you the following question. Here we
have the equation for the Carter-Wegman
通常，把新鲜值r视为MAC的一部分
MAC. As usual, you see the nonce r as
part of the MAC. And the second part of
MAC的第二部分我记为t。这是将一次性MAC
the MAC I'm gonna denote by t. This is
basically the one time MAC applied to the
应用到信息M上，然后使用伪随机函数加密
message M, and then encrypted using the
pseudo-random function applied to the
新鲜值r。我们把这个异或的结果记为t
nonce r. So we'll denote the result of
this XOR by t. So my question to
我给大家的问题是，给定特定信息m的
Carter-Wegman MAC对(r,t)
you is, given the Carter-Wegman MAC pair r,t
for particular message m, how
如何验证这个MAC是有效的？记得这里的算法V
would you verify that this MAC is valid?
And recall that its algorithm V here, is
是一次性MAC的验证算法
the verification algorithm for the
underlying one time MAC. So this is the
这是正确答案。想知道为什么，就观察这里的异或
right answer, and to see why, just observe
that this XOR here decrypts the quantity t
把量t解密成明文值了，即原一次性MAC
to its plain text value, which is
basically the original underlying one time
我们可以直接把它带入一次性MAC的验证算法
MAC. And so we can directly feed that into
the verification algorithm for the one
我想告诉大家的最后一种MAC
time MAC. The last type of MAC I wanted
to tell you about is one that is very
在因特网协议中特别流行，叫做HMAC。但在我们讨论HMAC前
popular in internet protocols. It's called the HMAC. But before we talk about the HMAC we
我们必须讨论哈希函数，特别是抵抗碰撞的哈希函数
have to talk about hash functions and in particular, collision resistant hash
我们下一章讨论
functions and we are going to do that in
the next module. So this is the end of our
这就是我们关于MAC的第一章内容。我想指出，有很美的理论
first module on MAC-s and I wanted to point
out that there's beautiful theory that
构建了我们看到的所有这些MAC。我给大家
went into constructing all the MAC-s that
we saw. I gave you the highlights showed
重点看了几种主要的机制，但其实有不少理论
you the main constructions, but
there's really quite a bit of theory that
深入研究了这些MAC的构建，如果想学习更多
goes into constructing these MAC-s, and if
you'd like to learn more about that, I
我列举了一些论文在这，大家可以看看。
我大概告诉大家它们是什么
listed a couple of key papers you might
want to look at. Let me quickly tell you what they
第一篇叫做三密钥机制，是CMAC的基础
are. The first one is, what's called the
three key construction, which is the basis
是一篇优雅的论文，给出了CBC-MAC的一个非常有效的机制
of CMAC. A very elegant paper that give a
very efficient construction out of CBC-MAC.
第二篇论文更技术点，但展示了如何证明
The second paper is a more technical
paper, but basically shows how to prove
CBC-MAC作为PRF的上界。第三篇讨论了PMAC
that bounds of CBC-MAC as a PRF. The
third paper talks about PMAC and its
及其机制，也是很犀利的文章。第四篇讨论了
construction. Again, a very acute paper.
The fourth paper talks about security of
NMAC和HMAC的安全性。HMAC我们下一章讲
NMAC and HMAC as well. HMAC we're going to
cover in, the next module. The last paper
最后一篇提出了一个很有趣的问题。
记得在我们所有的机制中
I listed asks an intriguing question.
Recall that all of our constructions, we
我们总是假设AES是一个16字节信息的伪随机函数
always assume that AES is a pseudo-random
function for sixteen byte messages and we
然后构建一个伪随机函数能计算长得多的信息的MAC
then built a pseudo-random function and
therefore a MAC for much longer messages.
这篇文章说，如果AES不是伪随机函数，但满足
某些弱化的性质
This paper says well, what do we do if AES
is not a pseudo-random function, but still
叫做不可预测函数，我们该怎么办？
satisfies some weaker security property
called an unpredictable function. And then
然后他们问如果AES仅为不可预测函数，不是伪随机函数的话
they ask if AES is only an unpredictable
function, but not a pseudo-random
我们还能构建长信息的MAC了吗？
function, can we still build MAC-s for long
messages? And so they succeed in actually
他们成功给出了基于弱假设，即AES是不可预测函数
giving constructions just based on the
weaker assumption that AES is an
而构建的机制。但是他们的机制远没有
unpredictable function. But their
constructions are far less sufficient than
CBC-MAC或NMAC或PMAC充分，如我们这三节所讨论的
CBC-MAC or NMAC, or PMAC that we discussed
in these segments. And so if you're
如果大家对根据分组密码，如AES，
构建MAC的不同观点感兴趣
interested in a different perspective on
how to build MAC-s from block ciphers like
请看这篇论文。这个领域有一些很好的开放问题
AES, please take a look at this paper. And
there are actually some nice open
值得研究。那么完整性的初章完结
questions to work on in this area. So this
concludes our first segment on integrity.
(口误：segment->module)
下一节我们讨论抗碰撞
And in the next segment, we're gonna talk
about collision resistance.